Yasin Aboukir earned the first place and the
most valuable hacker award at H1303 live hacking
event.
In this podcast, he'll describe his 10 year
long journey of how he got there.
You will learn what's his methodology, how
did it change or what are the underrated hacking
techniques.
But apart from this, he also does the hacking
while traveling the world and doing a lot
of sports and basically enjoying the life
and we'll also talk about this in this episode.
Enjoy.
Hello, Yassine.
Thank you so much for joining me today for
this interview.
For those viewers who don't know you, can
you please introduce yourself a little bit?
All right.
Thank you so much for having me.
Appreciate it.
So my name is Yassine Aboukir.
Born and raised in Morocco.
I'm 28 years old.
I'm based in France.
And I've been doing application security consulting
for a while.
But I've also been doing a lot of bug bounties
on this site.
So I started doing bug bounties in 2013 and
then so on.
I started on HackerOne, but I've done some
bug hunting like on and off platform for a
while as well.
So I worked for two years at HackerOne as
well.
I did some triage from 2017 to 2019 and then
just started doing bug bounties full time
again.
Also, the tragedy, I've done it part time.
So I was actually doing bug bounties as well.
So yeah, until now, I've been to a couple
of live hacking events as well with HackerOne.
It was an interesting experience.
And currently, I'm a member of the Hacker
Advisory Board at HackerOne as well.
And I do some pain testing with them too.
So most of the things that I do are kind of
related to HackerOne. 2013 is very early for
starting bug bounty.
How did you start?
How did you get interested in it back then?
Yeah, it was actually, it was the early days.
So basically, even before doing bug bounties,
I was doing hacking as a hobby.
So I really loved like finding security bugs
on software.
But back then, I had kind of a wrong idea
of how responsible disclosure worked.
So basically, what I was doing, I was finding
bugs on software, and then I would just go
straight and post them on the exploit databases.
Like back then was Milwarme.
I don't know if you know the name, but now
it's like exploit database.
So I just like post them there like for some
sort of clout.
I mean, to raise awareness as well, but I
had a wrong idea of responsible disclosure.
But then one day, I was just reading news
about cybersecurity news, and I stumbled upon
an article that was talking about HackerOne
and how you could actually now start hacking
legally and getting paid for that.
So I signed up immediately on the platform
in 2013.
But back then, there were not so many programs
like nowadays, there was just like a bunch
of open source projects like Python, Django,
Ruby on Rails.
I did not have like a very solid skill set
back then.
So it took me a while to actually find my
very first bug.
So yeah, that's how I got started on HackerOne.
And for how long did you do it full time?
I was doing it like starting from 2013 on
this side, like in parallel with my studies,
because I was still doing my studies.
So I've done it until 2018.
Like just on this side as a hobby.
And then 2018, when I graduated, I started
doing it full time.
Okay, and you also worked as triageur.
Yes, this look like how do you describe the
experience?
Basically, I joined the triage team in 2017.
After I passed the interviews, we were very
few people at the company, even at the triage
team, we're just like a couple of people like
me, Patrick, now I'm sick, a few other guys
like Everton from Brazil.
So the triage was still an early job back
then.
So we had to figure out all the processes
for triage, especially for triaging during
the life hacking events, because it's a live
triage.
So we had to figure out all the processes.
And like we were just triaging for a couple
of companies, it was just a few back then.
But now we started growing, growing, and until
the team got bigger.
It was an amazing experience because I had
exposure to this, the bug hunting community.
I was very fortunate to be invited to a bunch
of life hacking events to triage there.
So I got the chance to meet so many of the
hackers.
That's where I made so many of my connections.
It was just also like a great learning experience
for me as a hacker.
I mean, we're not going to deny that it was
like you triage a lot of reports coming from
hackers.
So you get exposed to a lot of knowledge there
as well.
It's just dealing with the team, the programs,
the companies, like having a different perspective
on the bug bounty hunting, just like from
a customer side and as well from the hacker
side.
So it was a great, great experience for sure.
And I did it for two years.
But yeah.
What do you think is the most important thing
that you learn as a triager that you just
can't learn from reading these closed write
ups?
Probably is that a lot of people, they all
have high expectations when they're submitting
reports.
And it's just like what I've learned is that
every company has different threat modeling.
So while a company may pay for a specific
class of vulnerability, another company may
not be able to afford that.
Or it's just because the issue is not really
as impactful as you may think.
So as a bug bounty hunter, always make sure
to lower your expectations when you're doing
hunting and not have high expectations.
And at the end, be very disappointed because
you were not you're not getting the outcome
that you were hoping for.
So I think that's one of the things I learned.
Okay, yeah, I would love to spend some time
working as a triager.
But I guess just for a month, because I don't
think I would actually like to work.
I would just like to see how it looks like
from the other side.
Yeah, but it is like for a month or a few
weeks.
I agree.
It is very, it is an interesting job for sure.
But also there is a lot of burnout in it.
Because like you're doing the same thing over
and over and it can be exhausting, like really,
really exhausting.
So it's not an easy job to do for sure.
Yeah, it looks like a very, very tough job
to me.
When you're hunting, what's your hacking style?
My hacking style.
So if you're talking about the methodology,
then in the early days of hacking, I actually
I used to do a lot of reconnaissance.
I do so much reconnaissance to have like a
certain data set that I can start hacking
on.
And then I started doing hacking manually.
So basically it was like a 50-50 kind of methodology,
like some recon and then you have a data set
and start hacking manually.
But then like I progressively actually started
focusing a lot or just on the main application.
So basically if I'm hacking on a certain application
and they have an open scope, I just focus
on the main app, the main functionalities.
And I go deep on understanding the app and
how it works.
Just like navigating it as a regular user
and writing down everything and then trying
to figure out where we can find the bugs from
there.
But in the early days, I was doing a lot of
recon and then manual hacking.
But now it's almost pure manual on the main
app.
So that's how I like to hack.
And when you open like a huge app with like
hundreds of endpoints and you know it's a
public bug bounty program probably looked
at by dozens of hunters, what do you do when
you start hacking on a target like this?
Actually that's my favorite kind of programs.
The programs that have like a complex application
with so many endpoints and so many functionalities
that are all connected together.
I think that's the best place where you can
find some interesting bugs, especially logical
bugs like everything is just connected.
When one side breaks, the other side will
break as well as a consequence.
So it's my most interesting kind of program.
When I started, it doesn't matter like there
were so many hackers that hacked it before
because I actually think that's a good sign.
It means that the program is a matcher program
because it's attracting a lot of hackers.
So it has a good hacker engagement.
So it's a good thing.
For example, if we look at PayPal, there are
so many resolved bugs.
There are so many hackers, phone bugs on PayPal.
But still, I've hacked on PayPal in the past
months, I still managed to find many bugs
on the application.
So it doesn't really matter that there were
hackers that hacked it before because like
the big programs like PayPal, for example,
they always have many code changes.
They push code on a daily basis, like building
up functionalities every day.
So there will always be bugs to be found.
So what I personally do is just say open the
app immediately and just start intercepting
traffic and just start browsing the application
as a regular user, making sure I'm very familiar
with each part of the application so I can
have a better visualization of the attack
surface.
And then from there, I can decide which functionalities
are attracting my attention.
If I get some interesting leads or something
that I think will be worth looking into.
So I just start from there and hack one functionality
by the other.
So I look at the functionality, I just think
what kind of vulnerabilities will be applicable
to this functionality.
What kind of vulnerabilities that I can test
against and I go from there.
Do you prefer client-side or server-side bugs
or you just don't care, you look at functionality
and you look for whatever you can find there?
I do a balance of both actually.
I like finding client-side bugs just as much
as I enjoy finding server-side bugs.
So basically, as I mentioned, when I'm testing,
I don't just go and look for certain type
of bugs or certain class of vulnerabilities.
I just go functionality by functionality and
see what kind of bugs will apply to it, either
client-side or server-side, it doesn't matter.
I think that's been helpful and that's one
of the advantages of my methodology, I guess,
so I don't miss out on other bugs.
So basically, I try to focus on high severity
bugs, basically, but while hunting, I might
stumble upon a medium, a low severity and
if it's worth it, I will definitely submit
it as well.
So just go with the mindset that you're going
to look for high severity bugs because they
pay more.
But then if I stumble upon any medium, I would
definitely submit them as well.
Okay, and what tools do you use and if you
use Burb, please mention some Burb extensions.
Yes, I mainly, as I mentioned, I used to do
a lot of recon and automation, but now that
I am focusing more on the app, I mainly just
use Burb suite.
So I use Burb suite and for the extensions,
I use the Turbo intruder for the race condition
kind of vulnerabilities.
I use Authorize.
It's an amazing extension.
I use it for privilege and access control
issues.
It just saves you a lot of time.
I use Paraminer.
It's one of my favorite as well because I
love to enumerate for hidden params and headers
as well.
So Paraminer, I use it a lot.
And what else?
I think that's basically it.
I use the ActiveScan++ as well sometimes.
It's a good scanner and there is the extension
that paints a bunch of random headers on the
request.
I forgot the name.
I use that one very well as well.
When you're browsing, it just paints a bunch
of random headers and checks the behavior
of the page.
I forget the name, but I use that extension
as well.
So I use InMap as well for port scanning.
And there are times when I do some recon for
sure.
So I would use E-MAS for subdomain enumerations.
I use the tool from Corbin, GAU, to find all
the endpoints.
This is actually, I love that tool.
I use it most of the time.
It's even if you're hacking on the main app
because you want to find all the endpoints,
the API endpoints, all the other index stuff.
So it helps a lot.
So InMap, GAU.
I use HTTPX to find the metadata, the title,
the server, the status, data like that.
So yeah.
And shout out to Project Discovery.
They have amazing tools.
I just want to give them a shout out.
Yeah, true.
Do you have better results now that you don't
do recon?
Not better results, but actually I mean better
payouts.
That's how I would put it.
Before when I was doing a lot of recon, it's
just a bunch, I find a lot of medium and low
CX vulnerabilities.
But now that I started focusing on the main
app, I actually noticed that the payouts are
far bigger.
Because the companies mostly appreciate when
you hack on the main app because they're more
interested in you to find bugs that affects
their customers.
But then when you do a lot of recon, it's
just like a bunch of outdated assets, maybe
subdomain takeovers, excesses on an interesting
subdomains where there is basically no impact.
But when you focus on the main app, there
is always impact.
There's always a security impact that you
know will matter to the company.
So I noticed the better payouts to say the
least.
Okay, what do you think is a bug class or
a technique or maybe a tool that you think
people undervalue?
A tool or a technique?
I definitely say fuzzing, like fuzzing all
the inputs, whether it's like a header, which
is like a typical input, which is like try
all kind of characters or kind of unique characters
and start fuzzing for all kind of stuff.
So I think fuzzing because you're pushing
the application to behave in a certain unexpected
way and then they always get some sort of
information from that behavior.
So fuzz all the things I would say.
What wordlist do you use for this?
Basically for fuzzing, I use Intruder, I use
the Turbo with a bunch of wordlists.
So that will do it if you're doing the web
application hacking, of course.
How often do you hack yourself and how often
do you collaborate with others?
For me, hacking, I think it depends.
I don't really have a fixed schedule so it
depends on if I feel like hacking.
But I think I would definitely average at
least maybe 25 to 30 hours a week of hacking
by myself.
I do collaborate as well.
It depends sometimes.
There are many times when friends of mine,
people that I know, they would reach out with
a certain lead, something they're working
on and they're trying to escalate it or you
just want to investigate what's happening
so they would just reach out to me.
Or I do the same as well when I know that
I'm working on something that is not within
my skill set and I reach out to people that
I know are good at that.
So I do collaborate occasionally as well.
I like collaboration.
You mentioned the skill set here.
I saw your presentation about AWS Cognito.
My question is how do you choose a subject
like AWS Cognito to do some research on?
If you remember, talk me through the first
time you saw this, through how did you research
what misconfigurations can happen and if you
did later try to find more instances of those
misconfigurations.
Yes, 100%.
So basically what happened with AWS Cognito
is that when I was hacking myself, either
doing penetration testing or doing back bounties,
I actually stumbled upon applications that
were using AWS Cognito and myself, I was not
familiar with it.
Just from observing those HTTP requests that
are being sent to the AWS, they were really
weird.
I couldn't understand them.
It was very hard for me to hack that application
because I was not familiar with the technology.
And then every time I looked up on Google,
for example, I looked up for resources, I
couldn't find anything that is just straightforward
like on how you would test for it.
There were some articles, there were already
a bunch of published misconfigurations, but
just the lack of information is what actually
motivated me to look into it a bit more and
just try to collect as much information about
the AWS Cognito, what it does, how it works,
and install it myself.
And that's how I started looking into different
configurations in the panel and then I started
reading the literature and already found so
many articles that were talking about those
and some of those misconfigurations as well.
There were some examples.
So, yeah, that's how I started and just gathered
everything in a nice presentation.
Before I did that myself, I found so many
vulnerable instances.
After that, I went back to all my back-bounty
targets that I knew were actually using AWS
Cognito after I got familiar with it.
And I found a bunch of other misconfigurations
as a result of that, but there was one with
Flickr that I had in my presentation.
That one was, I haven't talked about that
one yet.
It was a great finding where he managed to
take over Flickr using a bunch of AWS misconfigurations
in the app.
So, it was a great example to show in my presentation.
Yeah, I saw it in the recent case study in
Flickr.
It was disclosed.
Yeah, very nice bug.
Did you try then to also contact some, let's
say, automation-based hunters to maybe find
even more instances of programs using Cognito?
I did myself because I had my own automation.
I did run it across a bunch of back-bounty
programs.
I found a few, not that many, but I think
people, they wrote a Nucleid template afterwards
and they started scanning for it because I
had, after the presentation, I had so many
DMs from people trying to exploit those misconfigurations.
So yeah, I think people went and started looking
for it after that.
I saw you got the MVH award at the recent
lifehacking event.
Huge congratulations for this.
My question is, did you do anything differently
this time or is it just things just clicked
and you did more or less the same as usual?
Thank you so much.
I appreciate it.
For those people who are not familiar with
the MVH, so basically HackerOne, the platform,
they host a bunch of lifehacking events in
different cities in the world.
It could be in the United States, it could
be in the Netherlands, it could be in Portugal.
So these lifehacking events, they bring back-bounty
programs and they invite a bunch of hackers
based on different criteria to hack these
programs.
So I won the MVH at the end of the event,
there is a prize called the Most Valuable
Hacker.
It's a belt that you win for your own performance
based on other criteria.
So I think for me personally, for that event,
I was just very focused on the event.
What made the difference actually is me focusing
on the main app, just as I mentioned.
So that event, the scope was not an open scope.
It was not an open scope.
We had specific web applications that we were
supposed to hack.
I cannot name the company, unfortunately.
But yeah, I was very focused on the main app
and I spent a lot of time understanding how
that application works.
And I managed to find a bunch of account takeovers
and I think that one made the difference.
And also what made the difference is that
I did a lot of application-based reconnaissance
instead of just doing subdomain reconnaissance.
What I mean by that is just like fuzzing different
parts of the application, using it as a user
and just getting a good understanding of how
the app works in entirety.
So I did a lot of recon and I managed to find
so many endpoints just like in JavaScript
files for example, and that allowed me to
take over the account.
So I think that's what helped me win that
event for sure.
How do you specifically find endpoints in
JS files?
So basically, it depends on JavaScript, if
it's a bigger JavaScript, I use Link Finder.
It's a Python tool by Gerben from Meta Security.
It's a really good tool that helps you extract
all those endpoints from the JavaScript.
But sometimes I do manually go over the JavaScript
myself so I do not miss anything.
Because apart from the endpoints, it could
be hard-coded credentials, there could be
some client-side bugs like postMessageExcesses
or postMessageMisconfiguration that may lead
to a leak or something like that.
So there are some other things that you might
find in JavaScript files apart from the endpoints.
And for the endpoints, I also do like Gau,
as I mentioned earlier.
Gau is a really good tool.
It does find so many endpoints that I use
as a starting point to start hacking sometimes.
Yeah, in the recent case study, I even saw
an example of a bug that someone just found
some tokens in Gau, using Gau.
And they could just take, I think, reset people's
passwords with the tokens they found because
they were for some reason indexed.
And I really also like Gau because it just
gives you a basic idea of what endpoints is
the application using, what can you look,
what parameter names are used and so on.
So I also really, really like that.
Yeah, it's a very good tool.
You also mentioned that you do some consulting.
At the moment, what is your balance between
doing bug bounty and pentest, I believe, or
consulting?
I would say, actually, my bug hunting is taking
over a little bit.
So I would say probably like 70% bug bounty
is 30% consulting.
So I do consulting.
I have some clients of mine.
And I also do penetration testing with HackerOne.
They do pentesting consulting as well.
So we work with their own clients.
So if I'm not working with my own client,
I, there are occasionally when I get a pentest
signed from HackerOne, and I do it when I'm
not doing consulting, I can just focus on
bug bounty.
So I would say like 70% bug hunting and 30%
consulting.
If you could get the best parts of bug hunting
and the best parts of penetration testing,
what would such an engagement look like to
you?
Huh?
Well, actually, it's how HackerOne is doing
it, basically.
So they're doing the traditional penetration
testing, but in a crowdsourced way.
So it's like the best part of the bug bounty
is, which is like you're bringing different
skill set, different hacking methodologies
to the table.
And you also, it's a cost effective solution
for companies.
And you bring in the traditional part of the
pentesting, which is like, you're not as a
bug hunter, you're only focusing on finding
high in crates, but you can also find some
informatives and low severity bugs, and just
point out different areas where the company
could do better or could secure itself.
So it doesn't necessarily have to be just
finding criticals.
Yeah, so I think...
How does it specifically work?
I'm not familiar.
So basically, the HackerOne, they are doing
the scoping with the client, so it's like
setting the scope and setting the restrictions
and everything before the engagement.
And then for each pentest, there's like a
community of penetration testers working for
HackerOne.
So they basically assign the pentest to specific
hackers, depending on either the geographic
location, or the skill set, for example, if
it's a network pentest and we've got hackers
who are very good at network, they've got
relevant certifications, they might be assigned
to them.
So it could be based on the skill set, as
I mentioned as well, and also the availability,
if the hackers are available or not.
So there could be like a team of three hackers
working on a pentest with a lead, and someone
is leading the pentest.
So basically, you're given all the relevant
information that you need before you start,
and then you just start finding bugs and also
providing updates for the company as well
as for the whole team.
So it's just like a traditional pentest, where
you're just bringing different...
You're bringing people from different backgrounds
and different skill set.
And there is not pressure on the company.
Yeah, it's very interesting.
I heard something about HackerOne Pentest,
but I didn't really get into how it works.
Do you know how people can get involved in
doing this if they want?
I would say it's more or less a new offering
for them.
They're still working on scaling it.
So basically, now it's an exclusive community.
I think a lot of people were on board based
on their skill set, based on if they had an
experience before.
I think at one point, they were taking in
applications on the HackerOne platform.
If you go to your profile, I think there is
a form where you can fill it out with your
information and then you can apply to join
the community.
But I think they might have paused it for
a while as they try to onboard more customers
as well as figure out how to actually scale
it more.
It still requires a bit of manual work from
their part, so it's not really a fully automated
system yet.
If you were to, from now on, only do bug bounty
or penetration tests, what would you choose?
I would 100% do bug bounties.
I started doing bug bounties a long time ago,
so it doesn't really bother me.
I know there are pros and cons for each of
those, but I think I would probably be better
off doing bug bounties.
From a revenue standpoint, for example, I
think I'd make more doing bug bounties for
sure.
You just need to know what and where to focus
your time and effort on.
Consulting is good as well.
I mean, I would not say no, but I like the
thrill of bug bounties.
I think I like taking a bit of a risk.
I know bug bounty is not a very stable profession,
but I'm fine with that.
The more risk, the more reward.
It actually works quite well.
I've been listening to some podcasts about
unpredictable rewards that you should not
reward yourself every single time when you
do some good work.
It should be somewhat random that this is
a good way to do it.
And bug bounty is exactly this, because you
can put in the good work and not get a reward,
and another time you will get a reward.
So it works really well when it comes to this.
I think if you can combine both, that's a
win.
At least if you're having a dry month, as
we would say, you're not finding any bugs,
at least you have a revenue on the side.
So I think it depends on your personal circumstance
and situation.
For me, for example, I don't have people depending
on me, so I would be fine having a dry month
I think that would not be the end of the world
as long as you have a good foundation and
good base.
Yeah, that's actually my very next question.
For what type of people do you think the best
would be doing bug bounty full-time?
For what people it would be best to do freelance
pentesting?
And for what people it's just better to stay
at a 9-to-5 job?
So freelance pentesting, 9-to-5 job, and what's
the third one?
And bug bounty.
Oh, bug bounty.
I think for bug bounties, probably if you're
just like starting out in your career, I think
if you do bug bounties, it will be very beneficial
for you because you will build, you will have
a good experience, you will have relevant
experience or achievements that you can showcase
to land interviews or get a job.
Also it will give you some money on the side
to do whatever you want, like finance your
studies or do whatever.
So if you're starting out, I think bug bounties
can be amazing to do it on the side.
So even, but like once, and just as I mentioned,
it depends on your situation as well.
So if you're already into your career as a
penetration tester, for example, and for example
you have people depending on you, either you're
married or have kids, I don't think bug bounty
could be the best route as a starting point.
I think you might be better off if you actually
do some full-time job on the side and do bug
bounties when you have some spare time.
I think that would be a good way.
But it also depends.
I mean, there are people who are just resilient,
like I mean, they can take the risk, they
don't really mind.
Because like in bug bounties, you could have
like two months without finding anything,
you do not get paid, but then the third month
you just find some crazy bug and it will just
compensate for the two months that you feel
like you wasted.
But then it depends on how you perceive it.
Some people just like to do minimal work and
just get paid high rewards.
Some people, I don't know how to explain it,
but I mean it depends on your situation.
But just as I mentioned briefly, if you're
starting out, I think bug bounties could help
you a lot.
It helped me personally find my first job,
like with HackerOne for example.
But if you're already into your career, I
think it's better off if you just do a full-time
job and do bug bounties on this side.
I think that will be a lot better.
Does that make sense?
I agree with the...
Yeah, yeah, 100%.
It actually relates a lot to me because when
I was leaving my job, I knew that if I wait
too long and I get to like senior position
and good salary, I will always compare my
earnings after leaving the job to the senior
level salary and this is harder.
And also with years coming, with years I probably
will have more responsibility on my head,
having people counting on my salary and it
becomes, even though with more experience,
it's more logical to quit job, the better
situation is in the beginning when you're
just, as you said, you are free, you have
no responsibilities and also you just don't
have the...
You're not as accommodated in the corporate
world, for example.
Yeah, exactly.
And for me personally, I really value my freedom.
I value the flexibility that I have and I
put it above everything.
So just being self-employed works for me very
well.
So it depends on your aspirations as well.
Like if you want to go like climb the corporate
ladder as they say, I mean, good luck to you
but personally, I have different goals.
And I don't think being in the corporate world
is going to make it happen.
So it depends if it works for you, it just
works.
Yeah, yeah, 100%.
Also another thing that I've learned is it's
not like the next level, it's just something
different for people with different skill
sets and different values in life.
Like if you value independence, then obviously
you will not be happy in the corporate world.
But if you value stability, predictability
and safety, then obviously you shouldn't look
to people that, oh no, he's working, he's
self-employed, I should be as well.
No, it's your values, so you should do what's
best for you.
100%.
We'll speak a bit more about the free time
and everything.
Just a last question about the consulting
or penetration testing.
How do you find clients outside of HackerOne
Pen Testing?
So outside, I think when I first started out,
I think it was just me leveraging my own network.
When I worked for HackerOne, I was very fortunate
to have met so many hackers just being on
the live hacking events and such.
So these hackers, they work in different companies.
So when I was starting out in consulting,
I would reach out to them and they would actually,
a few of them responded positively and I would
land my first few gigs.
So basically I leveraged my network and then
I had a bunch of gigs and engagements that
came in through LinkedIn.
So I use LinkedIn as well.
Although now I don't really personally do
any cold reach outs myself.
I just built a network that I leverage to
find those gigs.
So I do have some offers that come from LinkedIn
as well.
I have success with back bounties as well.
There was a program, for example, that I hacked
a lot and they were really satisfied with
my results.
So they reached out to me to sign a contract
with them and do pen testing for them.
So that helps as well, doing back bounties.
I think it's a good way to meet people.
Just putting out myself out there, just from
social media, as they say, LinkedIn or just
on Twitter, for example, it's definitely been
helping expand my network.
We're just speaking at different conferences
and going there and meeting people.
So you put out your name out there and people
will definitely reach out to you if you've
got the right skill set that they want.
Any tips for people for building a good network
of people that they know and they can rely
on to contact them?
So 100% networking is important for tips for
people.
I would just say if you're a bug hunter, for
example, the first thing that you want to
do is join those online communities.
There is, for example, the HackerOne Discord
community.
You're going to meet so many people chatting
there every day, just exchanging knowledge
and helping each other.
There is the NAMSIC Discord as well.
There is a bunch of Slack channels that if
you just Google them, you're going to find
them.
So those are online communities that you're
going to meet like-minded people.
So just starting building contacts there,
chatting with people, and following them on
Twitter or maybe on LinkedIn.
Just make sure you give importance to some
social media networks like LinkedIn.
As bad as it looks for some people, it's actually
important to build your profile there and
follow relevant people in the industry and
just putting yourself out there.
I mean, that will bring you opportunities
for sure.
So as we mentioned, online communities, social
media, and just going to conferences.
If you go to conferences, I think I'm 100%
sure you will meet so many people.
You will not only just gain knowledge from
those talks, but you will also meet people
in those conferences.
As long as you keep an open mind and just
always try to take the initiative, talk to
people.
If you go to a conference, let the people
know on Twitter that you're there if someone
wants to meet up.
So those are ways that you can actually expand
your network.
It's not really rocket science or anything.
It's just like putting yourself out there
and getting out of comfort zone to meet people.
That's it.
And these people like- What are your favorite
conferences?
That would be definitely DEF CON in Vegas,
but there is also the CCC in Germany.
CCC is a hacking convention that takes place
in Germany.
I think when I was there in 2018 in Leipzig,
it was a pure hacker convention.
No corporate or commercial bullshit there.
Just like pure hackers doing their stuff,
creative stuff.
It was an amazing conference.
So I would say DEF CON in Vegas and the CCC
in Germany.
And there's also my new favorite one is B-Sides
Ahmedabed.
So I was there last year.
It was insane.
It was a huge audience, a lot of people.
They were just like seeking knowledge, very
curious and just wanting to meet up.
So it was a really big conference.
I really enjoyed it.
And the people that were speaking there, they
had really good knowledge, things to present
to the world.
So B-Sides Ahmedabed is one of my favorite
now.
I think I might be there this year again.
This is where you had the talk titled Mindset
of a Top-Tier Bug Bounty Hunter.
Is it this one?
Exactly.
Shout out to B-Sides now because I shared
it in the newsletter and I didn't write that
it was on the B-Sides conference in the newsletter.
And they wrote me on Twitter, can I add this
into the tweet?
But the tweet was already added and I didn't
do it.
So sorry B-Sides, but I'm doing the shout
out now.
I will do it next time as well.
This is far better.
There will be people watching.
Yeah, by the way.
Really good talk by the way.
So yeah.
And there will be for this year, it will be
actually, it will be Shops.
I think you just had an interview with him.
So Shops will be the keynote speaker and I
think he's a very good researcher.
It's going to be a really great talk for sure.
Oh yeah.
I can't wait.
I saw the recent research about the CCTLDs.
Yeah, that was insane.
I loved it.
Yeah.
So I know for a fact that you don't stay in
one place for the whole year.
You travel a lot.
So tell me what's your current lifestyle?
So yeah, I mean, I've been doing what we call
digital nomading since 2018.
So basically, so how it works is that I travel
and at the same time try to work.
So I've been doing it since 2018.
I've just been traveling to places.
So that's been my lifestyle, I mean, for almost
five years.
But now I'm actually slowing it down a lot
more than I used to before when I was changing
places more often and it was kind of exhausting.
And I was not very productive back then.
But now I'm taking it slow, like with my traveling
and hopefully spend a couple of months in
each place I go to.
So that's been my kind of lifestyle for a
few years now.
What are your favorite places?
I think I definitely have to go with Southeast
Asia in general.
I just love it going there.
And I would say Thailand is one of my favorites.
Indonesia, I had a really good experience
there as well.
Vietnam too.
So these three countries, I really love them.
So I would say Southeast Asia in general.
It's just like I feel at home there for some
reason.
And I love the people there, the culture,
the food.
It's just overall experience is amazing in
Southeast Asia.
So those are some of my favorite places for
sure.
Yeah, I was supposed to go there.
I wanted to escape winter this time in Poland.
And my plan was to go to Thailand.
But I just chickened out before because I
know it's far away, I go alone, blah, blah,
blah.
And I saw you on Instagram being in Tenerife.
And I actually went there because it's closer
to me.
It's still Europe.
I speak a bit of Spanish and I absolutely
loved it.
I will definitely continue in years to come.
That was I think you did the right choice.
Tenerife, I've been there as well, was really
good.
I loved it myself.
It's just the weather is amazing.
And it has a huge expat community with so
many digital nomads, like people that you
can actually meet with so many space, work
spaces where you can work from.
And just amazing.
I think you had fun there, right?
I had lots of fun.
And the community was the best.
As I said, I went there alone and I was afraid,
oh, no, maybe I will spend two and a half
months just sitting in front of my computer
and alone.
And in reality, I don't think I had so many
friends I would be in touch so often.
It was completely the opposite.
And that's what I'm telling people.
You just get out of your comfort zone and
just like face your fears and go check what's
out there in the world.
Just just go in.
You never know what you're going to experience.
So you went, you were afraid in the beginning,
but just then you went and you had an extraordinary
experience with this.
Yeah, and also you can come back to what we've
talked about previously about the like costs
of living and things like that.
You can also go to a country that's not necessarily
worse quality, but it's just cheaper than
the country you are currently at, depending
on where are you from.
If I'm if I'm not not mistaken, I think I'm
not the Thailand or Indonesia is just cheaper
than Europe mostly, right?
100% actually, it's not as easy.
It's cheaper than Europe.
That's that's 100% correct.
And the thing is that in those places, for
example, you can actually feel the value of
the dollar that you spend.
For example, in Bali, if I spend if I spend
600, six bucks, for example, for breakfast,
I would get the best quality breakfast there.
So the value, the dollar that you're spending,
there is so much value in it compared to when
you stay in places that are so expensive in
Europe, you pay loads of money with not much
value at all.
And then, like, for example, in those places
in Bali, for example, it's just amazing.
You pay, you pay.
I mean, it's getting expensive now.
It's like this is something that I've started
noticing after the COVID, everyone started
working remotely.
So these places are getting crowded now.
So it's actually getting expensive now, but
not as expensive as in Europe.
And still, you get a good value out of your
money that you spend there.
Everything is beautiful there, beautiful beaches.
You've got co-working spaces everywhere in
Bali, for example.
You've got a huge expat community.
If you're feeling bored, you want to go out
and meet people.
So everything you want is actually there at
a reasonable cost, at a cheaper cost if we
compare it to Europe, for sure.
Yeah, that's really awesome.
But one thing I struggled with was productivity.
And tell me what are the first things you
do to organize your workspace after arriving
in a new location?
Yeah, the productivity is the most important
one.
Actually, when I first started doing that,
like doing digital nomading, I was not as
productive as I wanted.
Because like every time I travel to a new
country, I was like, hey, I need to explore
it.
And then explore it, you go check out all
these places, spend a lot of time doing tourist
stuff.
And then at night, you go night clubbing,
and then you're not doing anything at the
end, you're just being a tourist.
And it took me a while.
Yeah, it took me a while to go from that tourist
phase to actually go with the mindset that,
hey, I'm here to work.
Mainly, that's my priority.
I set up my mindset.
I'm here to work.
And then everything on the side is just like,
it's secondary.
So I go with the mindset that I need to work
and I need to work out.
These two are very important.
And then if I've got spare time, then I can
go chill, visit places, meet people.
And when I go to a place, I mean, like when
I'm doing this lifestyle, if I want to be
productive, I would straight go to an Airbnb,
for example.
I get my own privacy and I make sure there
is a good Wi-Fi there, like a fiber optic
Wi-Fi that will not be interrupting.
And I make sure there is a desk where I can
work myself.
And or just if I don't have like a decent
Airbnb, I make sure to look up if there are
co-working spaces in the city that I'm going
to beforehand so that I can just go work straight
there.
If I'm having meetings with my clients, you
need to apply a place that is quiet and where
you can get things done.
So you need to do research beforehand or just
look for if there are some cafes where you
can work from and they tolerate people with
laptops because not all cafes can just let
you work there all day.
So you need to do some research before you
go to that place and just make sure to stick
to the regular schedule.
Like you make sure you wake up in the morning,
grab your breakfast and go straight to work.
It would be preferable if you actually go
to a working space because you put yourself
in the work mindset instead of you just stay
at home.
It can be confusing a bit.
So if you've got that option, you find a place
that is affordable, definitely my recommendation
is to go work from a workspace because you're
going to see other people's workings.
You're going to force yourself to actually
to work as well and you're just going to stick
to the schedule.
Maybe once you hit 5 p.m. then you give yourself
a break and you can go grab some drinks with
people or just chill at home.
So just try to stick to that schedule and
don't get distracted.
Especially if you have someone to travel with
that is also like have the same goal, that
would be a lot better.
So you can just motivate yourselves.
Yeah, yeah.
I actually really liked working from a coworking
space or a co-living space as well.
It was definitely a good experience.
100%.
And I also felt...
Yeah, yeah, go ahead, sorry.
I was just going to say it's like a close
family, especially if you're doing the co-living
thing.
It's just like living with the same people
for a couple of weeks and you just start bonding
and just like feeling closer together.
It's amazing.
Go ahead, sorry for interrupting.
Yeah, I had no idea what co-living is before
and I really, really liked it.
I wanted to ask you if, because I felt like
for this kind of lifestyle, I would rather
do pen tests and I would have some particular
specific project that I have to finish until
a specific day rather than having a bug bounty,
which is very hard to organize into a deadline
or something.
I completely agree with you.
Actually when I started in 2018, I was already
working with HackerOne on the side.
For me that was helpful because I could just
do my work with HackerOne and do not have
to care that much for finding bugs.
But I was also doing bug bounties on the side
as well, so that helped a bit.
And I completely agree that if you're going
to do this lifestyle, it's much better to
have something that you can rely on because
when you're traveling, you have so many expenses
that are just piling up and there are some
unexpected expenses sometimes, just like a
flight getting canceled, a hotel, just raising
prices in hotels.
There are so many unexpected expenses, so
it's much better for your mental health to
just have something that you can rely on for
some revenue and then you can always do bug
bounties.
But I mean, if you've got the skill set, you
know yourself, you're good, you could go without
finding anything for a month and then you're
going to find that one good bug that will
pay for your expenses.
I think that's fine as well.
So it depends on the person, but I think it
would be preferable if you have something
you can rely on for sure, 100%.
What's your hardware setup?
And I'm mostly interested in if you use an
external screen.
No, this is something that people actually
think funny about me because I always use
my MacBook laptop.
I don't use any external monitors.
I just actually recently, last year, I bought
my very first monitor because I'm traveling.
I left it at home, so I barely use it, only
when I go back to visit.
But for all these years, I just use my small
MacBook laptop, no crazy external monitors
or anything.
It works for me.
I mean, I do feel like I would be a bit more
protective if I use an external screen sometimes,
but it also does not bother me that much and
it's not going to make that huge difference.
But I think it's definitely more convenient
when you have a screen on the side that you
can use.
But yeah, for all these years, I've only used
my small laptop.
At one point, I had a 13-inch MacBook.
Now I have a 14-inch.
What are your tips for people working with
a single monitor?
I'm not sure I really have any tips.
It just depends how many screens you open.
I only open the one browser.
I mean, I open Chrome and then I open the
Burp suite, so I don't really find it hard
to browse between the two.
So it's not really a huge concern.
But it depends.
But I would assume for someone like you, you
might need some...
For someone like you with the editing, with
other things that you're doing, you probably
would need an external screen, right?
Yeah, yeah.
I also work quite a lot with...
Even in my home right now, I just have an
ultrawide monitor plus the MacBook normal
monitor and I kind of work only on the ultrawide.
And I've noticed that I just use the desktops
a lot and I switch between them.
And what I think is unless you are actually
doing something in one window and looking
at the result in another window, I think you
don't need external monitors to switch.
If you have like Burp open and the browser
open and you don't need to see at this literally
at the same time both, I think you're just
perfectly fine.
Because switching desktop is pretty much the
same time as switching your eyes.
And I get easily adjusted to this.
But for editing, yes, you need...
I don't think you need a lot of screens.
You just need a big screen and my 14 inch
is not enough.
Yeah, 100%.
I think if you can just adapt, I think it's
possible.
It's nothing crazy.
Also, I just, for example, open two screens
on my laptop and I just swipe between the
two like I put my Burp suite on the right
window and my Chrome browser on the left,
I actually just swipe between the two.
That makes it easier for me.
Also, if you're traveling, there are some
co-working spaces where you can rent a screen,
for example.
They do rent screens, monitors, so you can
do that as well.
Otherwise, I think I know some people that
use a huge iPad, use their laptop and then
iPad that works for them.
Yeah.
I did rent some screens and I saw, I think
I just saw an ad of like foldable triple external
screens that are like the size of a MacBook.
But I haven't tested it, but I don't think
I actually need this.
Another thing that I saw is I actually wanted
to see what are you up to on your Instagram,
but I think you deleted one.
What's your relationship with social media?
Okay, I actually disabled it.
I disabled it because I wanted to focus a
bit on work and not have too many distractions.
So my relationship with social media, I think
it's a healthy one, but I had to work to get
there actually because there were times where
I was very addicted to social media.
For example, like Facebook, I would post a
lot there.
And then I got rid of Facebook in 2020.
I disabled it indefinitely.
I never get there anymore.
Then I kept my Instagram and Twitter.
I use it professionally.
So Twitter has been very helpful, just building
the community there and interacting with like
minded people.
So I only exclusively use it to that and sometimes
post some updates and just get some info there.
So I use Twitter professionally.
I use Instagram to post my travel adventures
or travel pictures.
I love Instagram because I use it as a, it's
just like a book where I post all my past
travels and just like for a memory thing.
Some people think that I'm trying to do the
influencing thing, but I couldn't care about
that.
I love Instagram to post my stories there
and every time, save them to the highlight
and I go back and just can check everything
I've done in a trip, for example.
So yeah, I use Instagram more moderately.
I don't scroll up and down and watch reels
indefinitely.
I just post a story and that's it.
Yeah.
And also I do some periods where I just stop
using social media once and for all, like
for a month or for two months.
For example, this year I think I've done it
a couple of months.
Last year I stopped using social media for
three months.
These periods actually just help me detox
from these things as well as just like get
rid of distractions so I can focus a bit more
on work and be productive in other areas of
life.
Yeah.
Okay.
You also posted, when you were there, posted
quite a lot of updates from the gym.
How often do you do sports and what type of
sports?
I love sports a lot.
So I do different kinds of sports.
I do running.
I run half marathons.
I do a lot of running, actually, like 10Ks,
20K.
I do weightlifting as well, maybe four to
five.
I do like five sessions or six sessions a
week.
I love hiking as well.
I do trekking, just like hiking mountains
for a couple of days.
Surf skating as well.
Currently, I'm actually trying to learn surfing
and that's one of the things that I was doing
in Tenerife when I was there myself.
So I love Tenerife because like you have the
mountains, so I would go and run in the mountains
and hike there.
And then we have the ocean as well.
You can just go for surfing.
I love surfing there.
Amazing and consistent waves.
So I'm trying to learn surfing as well.
And I do other stuff on the side.
So I love sports and I just feel like it helps
me be a better person.
So I'm doing it regularly and I feel it has
huge, amazing outcomes on my life.
It just changed my life for the best.
Just like being in good shape, thinking clearly,
having the mental clarity.
Just like a couple of weeks ago, I was just
feeling a bit of a brain fog and then I just
like doubled down on my exercising, started
doing some intermittent fasting and it actually
helped a lot.
I feel a lot better now, can think very clearly.
So I think doing sports have actually changed
my life for the best and I definitely encourage
everyone else to do some sort of activity.
But whatever it is, as long as you're just
keeping yourself active, burning those calories
and making your heart work and getting strong.
Could you recommend some specific activities
for people that are listening to us?
They maybe spent whole days in front of the
computer and they don't really move much and
they would like to do something with their
life, maybe lose some weight.
What are some fun things they can do?
Yes, I think there are so many activities
that you can do that would actually fit your
schedule or fit your budget.
For example, if you don't feel like going
to the gym or you feel like if you go there,
you'd be confused, the first thing you can
just go out there, put on your shoes and just
go run, maybe run three kilometers in the
beginning.
Don't go hard on yourself, just run at a very
slow pace where you can maintain a conversation
with someone else.
And just run for three kilometers, that's
already something very good that you did and
then you can progressively increase the mileage
over time.
So running is a very simple activity that
you can do at your own pace, you don't have
to go faster to the extent that you hate it,
just make sure you're trying to learn and
enjoy at the same time.
So I would suggest just running and then if
you can afford the gym, it's not as expensive
as you might think, you just get a gym subscription.
There are loads of YouTube videos that you
can watch on how you can perform some different
exercises in the gym.
You don't need to use free weights, for example,
there are so many machines that are very easy
to use in the gym, you don't need any knowledge
or just watch some YouTube videos.
There are so many, I would say, workouts on
YouTube, you could just do like a 20 minutes
workout and after that workout, you will feel
so much better, you will think very clearly
and that will help you as a backbone hunter.
Like being in a good shape will definitely
help a lot more than you think because I think
a lot of people are neglecting their health.
Because I noticed myself back in 2017, 2018,
I was struggling a lot.
I didn't care that much about my own health,
I was not regularly exercising and I can always
like compare it to now where I maintain a
very regular exercising schedule, I eat a
clean diet, I can compare it to that period
and there is so much difference.
I just feel like my life has upgraded immensely
just by changing my lifestyle and exercising
and making sure I eat a clean diet.
So I think 100% will definitely help you be
a better version of yourself either as a bug
hunter or just a good person trying to live
their lives and do things in life.
Yeah, that's very nicely said and I also encourage
everyone definitely to do sports.
I personally also love doing sports.
I'm just happy doing them, I feel good in
my body.
I have lots of fun with friends doing different
types of activities.
So I definitely encourage everyone and I guarantee
that you will take the time off the schedule
but you will actually be more productive and
you will probably still do more in the same
amount of time.
You will have much more fun as well.
100% exactly.
Okay, man, the hour with you, talking with
you just flew by.
So we'll be closing the interview.
My last question for you is what are you looking
forward to achieve in the rest of 2023?
For the rest of 2023, first of all, I want
to have as much fun as possible.
That's always been for me.
I want to have fun and I also want to work
really hard on achieving a few things including
picking up a new research topic that I want
to work on for the rest of 2023 and hopefully
have something to present by next year.
So I just want to have a good time, have fun
and grind hard and meet as many like-minded
people as possible.
And hopefully our paths will cross at some
place.
You never know.
Yeah, I hope for it.
I'm pretty sure it will happen at some point.
And I wish you lots of luck with those plans.
If people want to follow you, where do they
go?
They can find me on Twitter.
My handle is @Yasineaboukir.
My first name, last name basically.
Thank you so much.
Awesome.
We'll also link this in the description.
Thank you so much for joining today.
I appreciate you.
Thank you for having me.
Hopefully next time.
This is the place where normally I would recommend
to you another episode of the podcast because
if you click another one, it boosts the algorithm.
But I am not going to do this today.
Today I just want you to take one advice from
this podcast that's relevant to you and do
something about it straight away.
If the fitness part is something about you,
just put on your training shoes and just go
for a run straight away.
If the traveling is something you were planning
but never got to doing, just go ahead and
book a flight.
Basically just do something right now.
For now, thank you for listening and goodbye.